Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Film Festival records, 1961-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Film Festival records 1961-2012
Ann Arbor Film Festival.
4 linear feet (in 5 boxes and 1 oversize folder)
2011122 Bp 2 UBPl
The Ann Arbor Film Festival is the longest-running independent and experimental film festival in North America. The collection consists of programs, posters and flyers, news clippings and articles about the yearly festival.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the organization (Donor no. 10635 ) and came to the library in 2011 and 2012.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Ann Arbor Film Festival is the longest-running independent and experimental film festival in North America. Internationally recognized as a premiere forum for independent filmmakers and artists, each year's festival engages audiences with remarkable cinematic experiences. The six-day festival presents 40 programs with more than 180 films from over 20 countries of all lengths and genres, including experimental, animation, documentary, narrative, hybrid and performance based works. The Ann Arbor Film Festival receives more than 2,500 submissions annually from more than 65 countries and serves as one of a handful of Academy Award-qualifying festivals in the United States.
The Ann Arbor Film Festival was started in 1963 by University of Michigan School of Art filmmaker/artist George Manupelli. The 1960s sparked rapid changes in cinema, thus challenging the art world to accept fresh ideas and talent. Manupelli took advantage of this shift and envisioned a festival that would serve experimental and pioneering filmmakers with the exposure, feedback and competition they desired. He designed his festival to be open to anyone who saw filmmaking as art. Since 1980, the Ann Arbor Film Festival has been independent of the University of Michigan as an independent non-profit arts organization.
Steeped in a rich tradition of ground-breaking cinema, thousands of influential filmmakers have showcased early work at the AAFF, including luminaries such as Kenneth Anger, Agnes Varda, Andy Warhol, Yoko Ono, Gus Van Sant, Barbara Hammer, Lawrence Kasdan, Les Blank, Chick Strand and George Lucas.
The AAFF is a pioneer of the traveling film festival tour and each year presents short film programs at more than 35 theaters, universities, museums and art house cinemas throughout the world. The festival began to distribute short films in 2008 and has produced three DVD collections with award-winning works available for home and educational viewing. The AAFF also presents and partners on events throughout the year, which have included screenings with the Ann Arbor Summer Festival, University of Michigan Museum of Art (UMMA) and Museum of Contemporary Art Detroit (MOCAD).
In 2006 the Ann Arbor Film Festival came under attack by politically-motivated censorship and saw its state funding revoked. In response, the AAFF launched the Endangered Campaign and raised over $80,000 in 4 months. In 2008 the AAFF received a 2-year grant from the Warhol Foundation to support the festival's initiative to support filmmakers as artists. In 2009 the AAFF received a grant from the Academy of Motion Picture Arts & Sciences to bring avant-garde film icon Kenneth Anger to the 48th Ann Arbor Film Festival.
The AAFF is a 501(c)(3) non-profit organization sustained by the generous support of donor and members, foundation and sponsors and audiences. The 50th Ann Arbor Film Festival took place March 27 - April 1, 2012.
The Ann Arbor Film Festival collection consists of programs, posters and flyers, news clippings and articles about the yearly festival. The collection includes materials representing each festival from the first in 1963 to the 50th in 2012. A few items relating to Cinema Guild or other Ann Arbor film societies are also included.
The collection is divided into four series: Program announcements and related, Press, Oversize posters, and Sound recordings.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Film Festival.; Film festivals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Manupelli, George.
Contributors:
J. Jasmine.--My new music.
- Program announcements and related
  This series forms the heart of the collection, containing programs, marketing materials, surveys, reviews, development documents, paste-ups of posters, and photographs in varying amounts and combinations for each festival from 1963 to 2012, with the exception of the third festival (1965) which is represented only by an oversize poster.
  - Undated (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
      (see also Box 5)
    - Photos, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1963 1st AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1964 2nd AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1965 3rd AAFF (Box 5)
  - 1966 4th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1967 5th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1968 6th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1969 7th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1970 8th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1971 9th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1972 10th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1973 11th AAFF (Box 1)
    (see also Box 5 and oversize folder)
  - 1974 12th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1975 13th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1976 14th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1977 15th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1978 16th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1979 17th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1980 18th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1981 19th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1982 20th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1983 21st AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1984 22nd AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1984 22nd AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1985 23rd AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1986 24th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1987 25th AAFF (see also Box 5 and oversize folder) (Box 1)
  - 1988 26th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1989 27th AAFF (Box 1)
  - General
    - Photos, Reception (Box 1)
  - 1990 28th AAFF (Box 1)
  - General
    - Photos, Reception (Box 1)
  - 1991 29th AAFF (Box 1)
  - General
    - Photos, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1992 30th AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1993 31st AAFF (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folder)
  - 1994 32nd AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1995 33rd AAFF (Box 1)
  - 1996 34th AAFF (Box 2)
  - 1997 35th AAFF
    - General (Box 2)
    - Surveys (Box 2)
  - 1998 36th AAFF
    - General (Box 2)
    - Surveys (Box 2)
    - Photos (Box 2)
    - Binder (Box 2)
  - 1999 37th AAFF
    - General (Box 2)
    - Photos, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 2000 38th AAFF (Box 2)
  - 2001 39th AAFF (Box 2)
  - 2002 40th AAFF, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 2003 41st AAFF (Box 2)
  - 2004 42nd AAFF, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 2005 43rd AAFF (Box 2)
  - 2006 44th AAFF
    - General (Box 2)
    - Photos (Box 2)
    - Hospitality Binder (Box 2)
  - 2007 45th AAFF (Box 3)
    - General (Box 3)
    - Photos (Box 3)
    - Survey (Box 3)
  - 2008 46th AAFF (Box 3)
  - 2009 47th AAFF
    - General (Box 3)
    - Photos (Box 3)
    - 826 Michigan Workshop Surveys (Box 3)
  - 2010 48th AAFF
    - General (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Printed (Box 3)
  - 2011 49th AAFF (Box 3)
  - 2012 50th AAFF (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Archive of Awesomeness (Box 3)
    - Archive of Suck (Box 3)
    - Manupelli, George (Box 3)
- Press
  The Press series consists of newspaper clippings from 1999 through 2012, with a few earlier items including one article about George Manupelli from 1961, predating the Ann Arbor Film Festival.
  - Undated (Box 4)
  - 1961-1968 (Box 4)
  - 1999 (Box 4)
  - 2000 (Box 4)
  - 2001 (Box 4)
  - 2002 (Box 4)
  - 2003 (Box 4)
  - 2004 (Box 4)
  - 2005 (Box 4)
  - 2006 (Box 4)
  - 2007 (Box 4)
  - 2008 (Box 4)
  - 2009 (Box 4)
  - 2010 (Box 4)
  - 2011 (Box 4)
  - 2012 (Box 4)
- Oversize posters
  The Oversize posters series parallels the Program announcements and related series, containing material too large for the standard boxes used in the first series.
  - Undated (Box 5)
  - 1st-5th (Box 5)
  - 6th-10th (Box 5)
  - 11th-15th (Box 5)
  - 16th-20th (Box 5)
  - 21st-25th (Box 5)
  - 26th-30th (Box 5)
  - 31st-40th (Box 5)
  - 41st-50th (Box 5)
  - Paste-ups
    - Undated (Box 5)
    - 1st-20th (Box 5)
    - 21st-50th (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1st-50th (Folder UBPl)
- Sound recordings
  The Sound recordings series contains one phonograph record, an LP by J. Jasmine (Jacqueline Humbert) entitled My New Music, described as "made especially for the 16th Ann Arbor Film Festival, 1978." One of the tracks on the record, "Rented Car, Painted Woman, Borrowed Time," is by George Manupelli.
  - My New Music, by J. Jasmine (Jacqueline Humbert), "made especially for the 16th Ann Arbor Film Festival, 1978" (Box 1)
    1 phonograph records